good evening good evening everybody dj could we have in-house audio up just a smidge if it's possible david maybe just to try just because i'm usually a little bit louder and i'm this close so i can see him how about now that's perfect thank you i appreciate it i don't want to yell all right good evening i now call this july 22nd 2025 meeting of lancaster city council to order this meeting and its participants are being recorded please take a moment to silence your phones and your devices if you haven't done so already during this meeting there will be several opportunities for public comment the first is a general public comment period for residents that have registered in advance to speak about items that are not on the agenda residents might also comment on individual items on our legislative agenda that's section 9 on our agenda this evening and finally a second public comment period will be at the end of our agenda for any other speakers wishing to address council all speakers will be reminded to begin with their name and block of residence for our meeting record and address their comments toward council please be advised that public comment is not a question answer period all comments are limited to three minutes per speaker to keep time i'll be using a timer light here when a green to three minutes has begun when it blinks yellow there's one minute remaining and when it blinks red three minutes has been exhausted if a speaker continues after three minutes i will kindly ask that they end their comment i appreciate everyone's cooperation to maintain order and equal time speakers addressing city council and members of the audience will be expected to conduct themselves in an orderly manner and remain respectful of others and now for all that are willing and able please rise for the pledge of allegiance mr harris would you please call the role of members yes madam president our first item in front of us this evening is the approval of the minutes of our july 8th 2025 agenda uh at counselors um oh i will hear a motion for that motion to approve second thank you we have a motion and a second for our meeting minutes any counselors have comments on the minutes
hearing none Mr. Harris Mr. Moon aye Mr. Arroyo aye Mr. Cleese aye Ms. Craig aye Ms. Diaz aye Mr. Hirsch aye and President Begay aye
the next item on our agenda is proclamations honors awards and resolutions of recognition confirming Mr. Harris that we have none of those
this evening is that right we do not have any this evening thank you very
much councillors with unless there's any specific objection I would like to move the report of president of council to this point in the agenda I appreciate that given that many of you are here tonight regarding the planned data center on Greenfield Road I would like to begin with some updates that are pertinent the these updates for a council and the public were shared during an earlier press briefing this afternoon it was attended by the mayor and representatives from Carissa Technology Parks and Wilson and Turner construction this is particularly important as of at least 530 I hadn't seen any coverage on this and I think it's important that the information is disseminated to the public so here is a rundown you're gonna hear me talk a lot so get ready to existing and industrial sites at 216 Greenfield Road and 1375 Harrisburg Pike are being developed by Carissa Technology Parks and Machine Investment Group the construction is being managed by wolson and turner construction only one of those properties 216 greenfield road has any active building permits under review these are not definitive there are not definitive plans for 1375 harrisburg pike at this time construction at greenfield road has begun and is expected to be completed in summer of 2027. the city is required to comply with existing legislation and state law in dealing with property owners and their use this includes the city's zoning ordinance subdivision ordinance and land development ordinance that complies with the pa municipality's planning code and all state laws a note on zoning as you may know the city determined that zoning was allowed by right meeting the current zoning applies to the proposed use the future land use map of our future lancaster also designates these areas of the city as appropriate for high density industrial and regional commercial development i want to also note that changes to the zoning ordinance require a lengthy process including review and approval by the county planning commission several public meetings and a public hearing and under the matter of the building permit based upon the building permit applications that were submitted to the city for 216 greenfield road none of the work currently being performed or planned under those permits constitutes a land development or subdivision subject to planning commission approval if future work extends beyond the existing buildings footprint the land development process would be applicable city oversight there has been and continues to be considerable review and oversight done by city staff including building permit applications reviewing to review to assure conditional approval and compliance with all applicable codes including construction demolition and fire mitigation updates on water usage these sites will not rely on large volumes of water for cooling purposes in contrast to other data centers these sites will use fans for air cooling additionally existing ordinances protect the city from having to provide water to any customer under any circumstances most especially if we do not have the capacity to do so i want to reiterate and this is important that existing ordinances already ensure that we are not required to provide water in the instances where we do not have capacity a note on power carissa technology parks is working closely with ppl to assure electrical needs are met without impact to their customers they reported this afternoon carissa is paying for upgrades to electrical electrical substations on the greenfield property to reinforce the power grid ppl is building a new switch yard as well as adding resiliency to the local grid council will continue to monitor these updates from that utility a note on fire safety fire chief hutchinson has been involved in the review to ensure that the state-of-the-art fire prevention systems are in place and ensure that our firefighters are prepared for any emergency response notes on noise the developers have assessed the potential for noise impact at greenfield road and they have found through their review that the data center will be noise neutral meaning the noise generated by the data center will be at the level of or less than the current noise level at the site this is yet to be independently evaluated by the city council will also continue to ensure the public is updated on this matter a note on jobs that was shared at the press conference this afternoon the city is pleased that a local construction company wolson is undertaking this project generating local employment of between 600 and a thousand construction jobs as well as 150 approximate new permanent jobs in lancaster i do want to make notes on city benefits that were shared at the conference the productive use of these sites will have tangible benefits to the city's revenues and thus the taxpayers the sale and redevelopment of these properties impact the real estate transfer tax assessed value for real estate taxes and build that permit building permit revenue another note in addition to the tangible economic benefits from the city on the city's revenues mayor sirachi stated she will be negotiating a community benefit agreement that will demonstrate the Carissa technology parks and its tenants are committed to being good neighbors here in Lancaster and more details are will be forthcoming and council will monitor those updates I also want to make a note about opportunities for future engagement on this matter Carissa announced their intention to hold a town hall in the future so directly with the developer to discuss more details as they become available related to power sources etc so we will continue to push out updates as we learn from them when they will hold those that concludes my council president's report this evening members of council thank you for allowing me to move that forward in our agenda this evening we will now move into our first public comment period this is reserved for residents who have contact the city prior to this meeting to request the opportunity to address council this was before the 2 p.m. deadline to get our meeting materials together duration of comments are again are limited to three minutes I've asked mr. Harris to please put a list of those who have registered for public comment in advance on the screen so that you can know when you're next and proceed to the microphone there just a note please begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting record and as you might be the first person to reach the microphone you may need to turn it on it may already be gone and I'll be keeping time thank you
so much mr. Harris our first speaker our first speaker is Tony Hopkins good
evening sir can you just make sure there might be a button or not it's okay we're working on borrowed tech there we go thank you so much madam president madam
Mayor. I am now a retired attorney. I practiced law here in the city for many, many years, both for a rather prominent firm and I had my own office for 10 or 11 years on Walnut Street. I'd like to begin my comments by paying my respects to Councilman Amin. I've known the Councilman since he was a 12-year-old boy playing right guard for the East Peak Bulldog football team. My son was playing right tackle on that team. So, Councilman, it's good to see you raised up to a position of prestige I never doubted you would achieve that so my comments about traffic the other about two weeks ago I was driving north on Mary Street I I want to say I went home on Wallace Street every day for 30 plus years so I was trying to turn left on the Wallace Street and I couldn't see a thing okay I had a conversation with one of your staffers when I brought this to the attention of the clerk and she told me that the city traffic plan believes or is drawn in such a way as the quote unquote daylight those intersections so that people can see oncoming traffic I'm here to tell you it's a fiasco okay I waited and waited and waited I eventually nosed my way out and as i looked on my right there were three cars doing at least 35 miles an hour coming up that incline on walnut street everybody accelerates to come up walnuts if i had waited two more seconds there would have been a four car collision at that intersection if i had been crossing walnut street it would have been a t-bone collision okay since then i've made at my business to pay more attention when i drive out walnut street and i'm going to tell you that's it that problem exists at every intersection you have on walnut street and lemon street except the ones where you have traffic lights you daylighted those intersections by removing one parking place that is near that is not nearly sufficient it is literally impossible to see the oncoming traffic heading west on Walnut Street pretty much at every intersection you have it's extremely hazardous situation I will tell you furthermore that conversation I've had with a young person a young woman who tells me that a lot of the young moms on those streets are extremely concerned about the speed of the traffic coming up on the street and the inability to see at intersections it's an extremely extremely hazardous situation complicated by the bike lane and the X doubt lane you have so cars doors can open and not interfere with the bike lane I'm not an anti bicycle guy when I was a young man I had a very significantly high level bike I put it on my shoulder I flew to England and bicycle okay so this is it's a severe situation you need to pay attention to it thank you thank you sir mr. mr. Harris
our next speaker next speaker is Mary McClain thank you and just as a reminder
just you're already doing it please begin with your block thank you right into the mic and I know that the one is going to be cooled by air instead of water but air cooling could mean significant noise pollution for anyone living within a quarter mile of it the decibels reach well over those considered safe for humans near air cooled data centers lancaster city zoning told me today that in practice they can only take the word of the applicant and can't determine ahead of time if the business will be noisy in fact city zoning said that the data center company met with city officials and one of the things they discussed was noise the city was convinced by the response of the company that there would be no noise problem but this is just based on what they want to say in fact if you look at the other data centers around the country noise is a problem the city okay the city noise ordinance can come into play only after the center is built and operating at which point it would be impossible for residents to get any enforcement and pa state has no noise laws that might help and i couldn't tell from what you did and you've said in your update whether city officials have promised tax breaks to the data centers there are 170 properties in the city that have local tax exemptions mostly hospital church and school the state of pa is about to pass bills with incentives to lure ai data centers to our state most or some municipalities and states have offered tax breaks and regretted it later because they are difficult to end washington state approved tax breaks for data centers without public input I might add and are suffering that loss of revenue for very few jobs that were created by having the data centers there the typical data center employees 50 to 200 permanent technical and maintenance jobs I know they told you something like up to a thousand that's not what the usual one is so if the data centers proposed here in Lancaster do not pay local taxes there will be no value to having them here other than ridding ourselves of the problem of an empty warehouse residents may find themselves funding new transmission lines down the road as has happened in some municipalities something else to think about the city approved demolition of the Greenfield site building June 30th but if the approval was made public it was not front page news as perhaps it should have been miss McLean we've
reached three minutes okay thank you Mr. Harris our next speaker please next speaker is Jackie Snyder is Jackie Snyder present this evening Mr. Harris
our next speaker and the next is Rachel Baer thank you is Rachel with us this
evening we will move our next speaker is Amy Ernst good evening my name is Amy
Ernst I live on the 800 block of Columbia Avenue in the city I'm here to propose a textual amendment to the zoning ordinance to reclassify data centers moving forward as digital infrastructure facilities permitted only in general industrial zones subject to conditional use review we all know these are not wholesale trade and storage facilities they don't use they don't store anything traditional and they don't do it in a traditional way and wholesale trade and storage facilities require one of the lowest levels of oversight these types of centers require far higher levels of oversight it's like calling them storage facilities and requiring such low levels of oversight is like calling a toxic waste facility storage because it stores toxic waste whether it's a massive drain on the power grid or water supply that residents might carry the weight of or the alarming health effects already being seen in communities across the us from their cooling fans and there will be more effects to come this is the wild west for for these companies um but these data centers do have the power to to have a really negative impact on this incredible city other counties are starting to take action the language that i was focusing on which i sent in emails earlier today is a digital infrastructure amendment is from frederick county maryland where they're not letting these companies bait them and harm their communities i know people many people here today have worked really hard over the past 20 years to build this city into one of the most desirable small cities to live in please don't let it be destroyed by letting big tech walk all over us they'll fly in their specialists they won't create many new jobs here the construction jobs will be temporary they'll take what they need they'll make huge profits and they'll just leave the city in its wake as i said before these are not traditional storage facilities so i am proposing this textual amendment whether it can apply to these data centers or any moving forward they should not be classified as wholesale trade and storage and they need new classification with higher oversight and conditional use
permitting thank you mr harris our next speaker please our next speaker is jontel toland and i'll just remind folks we have the list and the order they were received on the screen behind us
good evening good evening uh john tell tolan first and only block of uh wise app um i don't come here often when i'm here you usually know there's a problem uh there's tons of people here uh counselor bakey i heard what you said and thank you for saying that at the beginning but i still think that many people here are probably still skeptical and concerned And I hope that there is some transparency that continues to happen going forward. And I hope that people continue to come and check on them and see what goes on. I had a lot of things that I wanted to say, and I think I will hold off on some of them. But I did email you all as well. I think that we're all still very concerned about the impacts. And the things that you said still didn't really do much for me. I'm still very concerned, and I would like to see you guys address this more and do your own research as to the impacts of Memphis, Tennessee, for example, and what's been going on there and the town hall meetings that have been held with no accountability and no transparency whatsoever after the fact. and you giving the spiel of what you just said it's it's kind of it's to me it sounds like fluff and I believe I only heard in reference to like Greenfield Road and I think I there's a there's another site on Harrisburg Pipe that's being looked at right I just think that there should be a big firm stance that is a collaboration between the community and City Council because we really have to cut this off at the head before anything else goes any further I don't think that we should even be considering that any of these facilities are anywhere in the county so I'll keep an eye out thank you thank you
mr. Tolan just for clarification and I appreciate your words the information was provided at my report at the top of the meeting was a way to disseminate the information that was given at the press event earlier tonight um not necessarily a a judgment statement but the factual information that was shared so we will continue and i i do want to and i think i've reiterated this to some of you who may have reached out to me personally that members of council are interested in in preserving the public safety uh in resources and interests in this and have been working as we've been made aware of this which was not terribly long ago but i want to ensure that there is continued oversight so but i appreciate your words and thank you for that mr harris our next speaker our next speaker is brian nelson as uh mr nelson is coming forward i'll just remind everyone that the names are on on the screen in the list in the order in which they were received so the next folks can be ready good evening um hi i'm brian
nelson i live on the 100 block of east lemon and um i wanted to talk about the planned data center as well i think that i have an issue with two major corporations telling us what will and will not be good for our citizens i think that's not for us to decide and i think that we have these data center companies coming here trying to use up all our power because they don't think we have enough to fight back and i think that i have an issue with that um my major issue is uh to use computers you have to use a lot of energy you create a lot of heat that burns a lot of carbon and they're going to set that off into lancaster county with these planned data centers in these areas that are going to create noise pollution whether you like it or not and in fact it takes more energy to cool these data centers than they create computing power so there's nothing about these data centers that screams energy efficiency to me and we're already getting hit with hikes from ppl um i don't believe them when they say i'm not going to get a hike i don't believe that for a second and i think that is on you guys as city counselors to actually what they said is take a stand and let us know whether or not you agree or disagree with having this data center in our community because i think that the community right now is ready to tell you that they don't want it and i think that that's on you guys to do your job and make sure that they've been heard that's all they have to say thank you sir mr. Harris our next speaker
please our next speaker is Mimi Shapiro don't think I saw me this evening mr.
Harris our next speaker then the next is Emma Burgess good evening yeah like you
said my name is Emma Burgess I live on the 600th block of West Vine Street and I hold a master's degree in electrical engineering I really thank you president bake a for the updates I think that was really helpful context and actually I I really appreciate the comments by Brian. I'm kinda gonna provide a little bit more context in terms of the numbers. In three minutes, I really only have time to talk about the utility impacts of building a data center. I think you've probably read the LNP article from July 16th, but let me quickly reiterate a few points. The data center is estimated to consume 100 megawatts of power and would run 24 seven. That is 70,000 megawatt hours per month. The average Pennsylvania household, according to the EIA in 2022, consumes 854 kilowatt hours per month, which means that the data center would consume the energy equivalent of 85,000 homes in Lancaster on the low end. There are 21,000 homes in Lancaster City, according to the Census Bureau. Adding a data center would use the energy equivalent of four times the entirety of Lancaster City houses on the low end. On the high end, it would use the energy equivalent of the entirety of Lancaster County households. Really quick, I'd like to note that the LNP article misleadingly gives numbers for one megawatt, which is 100 to 300 times less than this proposed data center, which they say would power 400 to 900 homes for a year. And using recent data from the EIA, I get 850 to 2,500 homes, which is twice as much. I spoke to the reporter. His numbers were based on 2001 figures and had some assumptions in there. After speaking together, he agreed that the numbers I just told you were correct. Regarding the water cooling to fans cooling, I think that would increase the amount of energy used there. Either way, that puts immense stress on a power grid that is already getting increasingly expensive for us. Like Brian said, from January 2020 to today, electricity rates have gone up by 50% according to PPL's own data records. Across news sources and climate advocacy organizations, experts always agree that when data centers are built within an existing power grid, everyday consumers always pay the price. Lancaster City residents are already struggling to pay those bills. This would make things worse. It's not just the cost to increase the power grid, it's the cost to maintain a much, much, much, much larger power grid, and we have no guarantee that Carissa is going to pay that cost forever. Senator McGormick has been touting the economic benefits of this data center, but I ask you to consider, council, are 150 jobs worth the decades-long price that Lancaster residents are going to have to pay this data center and i really have to ask you to consider to put safeguards against this kind of development that jeopardizes the future of lancastrians for decades to come please consider public input before allowing us to go forward thank you for your time thank you mr harris our
next speaker next speaker is dan weigel good evening sir dan weigel the only block of clarendon drive data centers are not warehouses they do not merely store products and should not be classified as wholesale trade and storage data centers consume massive amounts of dirty fossil fuels they pollute the environment and they are hazardous to the health of those living nearby i am not willing to trade my health the health of my neighbors or the health of the environment for corporate profits i hope that each of you are also unwilling to make that trade we are not helpless bystanders to the corporate profit-driven ai so-called revolution where the people have a choice and we do not want it this is a bipartisan consensus with a recent lnp poll showing more than twice as many residents opposing the data center as favoring it so on a local level we must say no to data centers let us choose people the ones living and raising families here right now not corporate profits i understand that saying no to data centers is not easy in a legal sense what i ask is this a text amendment to the zoning ordinance to reclassify data centers from their current status as wholesale trade and storage instead i propose a new category digital infrastructure facilities that will require oversight regulation and a lengthy review process with ample public input prior to any permits being issued regardless of whether it is too late to stop the first facility please act urgently to protect our community moving forward data centers are a new and unique form of harm and they require an appropriate response i get that it is a long process to change the zoning ordinance let's start that process now thank you thank you mr harris our next speaker our next speaker
is abby haney good evening good evening my name is abby haney i live on the 600 block of east madison street and i am like so many others here about the ai data centers i have some major concerns um so i want to talk a little bit about electrical usage but so many of you have already made really great points and are far more educated than i am but core weave which is the same company that like would operate here they actually have a facility in denton texas and it's already been shown that they've doubled the amount of electricity used in denton using a majority of the local power system capacity these facilities like others have mentioned have to be powered 24 hours a day seven days a week 365 days a year and a hundred megawatt facility consumes as much electricity as a hundred thousand households annually and oftentimes residential users are left putting the bill for this huge power drain because power companies subsidize the cost of these data centers by passing along rate increases to residential customers my pp and l rate has not gone down in seven years that i've lived here so i can't imagine that it will then in regard to the belief that the building of these data centers will help the local job market especially for the construction industry i'm old enough to remember when they said the same thing about fracking instead they brought workers from out of state and then things when things were all said and done these companies would pack up and leave the community to deal with the environmental fallout i saw the information from the mayor's office that these plan to be air cooled not water cooled and i just want to ask can you confidently say that they'll remain that way what happens when the center inevitably expands and air cooling is no longer cost efficient or effective for coreweave i could also talk at length about how climate change is not going to spare us and will cause shrinking of our water tables and that lancaster has the second worst air quality in the mid atlantic and 22nd worst in the country i'm calling for a change in zoning laws like so many others have this center falls under wholesale trade and storage which is outdated and is not applicable to this proposed data data center in my opinion it fails to account for the unique risk and harm associated with data centers and what happens when these facilities want to expand outside of the footprint can you make a commitment for an honest storm water evaluation like was mentioned in by the mayor's spokesperson in the lmp article earlier today if it's found that it would negatively harm lancaster can you truly say you would deny their request to expand i also have questions about the good neighbor bargaining agreement that was mentioned what kind of public input will we have on that or is the mayor going to make those negotiations unilaterally we deserve public input from the beginning of this process not after the wool has already been pulled over our eyes our community deserves better than a huge fast-tracked energy eating project that will affect our decade affect our community for decades to come thank you thank you mr harris our
next speaker our next speaker is david devries good evening debris thank you uh david debris
400 block of east grand street um a lot of people said a lot of things better than i could they did a lot more research than i had time to but i'll just say i'm here to ask you to put our community ahead of outside business interests and to deny this in any way possible these data centers The link between environmental destruction is clear from so many other examples that have already been said today. They're going to use so much power, massive amounts of energy, which will accelerate climate collapse, not just here, but everywhere around the globe from all these data centers. Terrible, terrible for the environment. And the harmful pollutants that they also may cause are going to harm our most vulnerable residents, as well as anybody else in the area. but also want to say the ai industry itself is the project of billionaires who seek to cut costs by making our jobs obsolete we don't need to scab ourselves we don't need to let these plutocrats into our lives to run things just because they have money i don't think we need to give them the tools to take away our livelihoods while also destroying our environment around us we have the choice to stop these things and we need to decide who we work for Do we work for these people just because they have money, they can come into our community and destroy the environment, or do we have the option to stop that from happening? Thank you.
Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker.
The next speaker is Christine Kennedy.
Good evening. My name is Christine Kennedy. I live at 10 North Market Street in downtown Lancaster, and I appreciate the opportunity to speak to the Council and all of those that have spoken so far, to Mayor Sirachi, Council President Bakay, City Council members, and the journalists that are in the house. I'm writing to you, and we'll forward this in an email, in regards to the proposed air cooled aspect of the data centers in Lancaster City and their environmental impact. I read in this morning's LMP paper, as others have said, that the data centers will initially be air cooled, mitigating concerns that were voiced earlier about the water concerns. I'm someone who has experienced the noise pollution impacts that data center fans firsthand. I want to voice my concerns with the hope that we can accelerate city policy to address this in the future and as much as we can with those facilities that have already been approved earlier this year my husband and i visited a family member who lives near the data center that's featured in the time magazine article we're living in a nightmare inside a health crisis of a Texas bitcoin town. The article reveals the health impacts to neighbors, animals, vegetation caused by the constant noise from the fans that cool the data center, including loss of hearing, fainting spells, debilitating vertigo, and nausea. The fans are heard miles away. My cousin's home is five miles away and we can hear the fans there. The recent LNP articles note that the city classified a data center land use as wholesale trade and storage. The regulations related to that do not take into account the unique impacts. As a former urban planner, I turned to the American Planning Association for Resources and found zoning for data centers and cryptocurrency mining. article addresses that impact for data centers to look at noise as well as water and power i ask that you assure that the city's noise ordinance covers and controls this type of noise source so that lancaster city will not have the same situation as granbury texas thank you thank you
mr harris our next speaker next speaker is rachel kruger thank you good evening uh thank you uh
rachel kruger and i'll admit that while i do live outside of the city itself i do live on greenfield road about a half mile from the proposed data center i appreciate you with providing me a moment to discuss proposed data centers to provide you a little bit of background so you know where i'm coming from i hold a degree in geology and have worked in the environmental field for the last eight years as others have told you ai data centers present a number of environmental hazards we're seeing that now as more and more of these facilities make national headlines for churning out enormous amounts of greenhouse gases and other compounds inextricably linked to cancer and cardiovascular and respiratory disease so as another concerned citizen i have questions some you did touch on at the beginning of the meeting but i have a few more concerns for example why an ai data center i understand that not all land will meet all use criteria i understand that after years of industrial use the process of bringing that land up to something like residential use would be incredibly costly red rose commons comes to mind that area is commercially developed because it was previously occupied by the aluminum industry redeveloping that area to residential standards wasn't feasible so instead we made it commercial and it created jobs and brought revenue i also have questions like how will our energy infrastructure be protected in other communities of similar facilities we have seen the increased energy used by these data centers get passed on to residents should we expect to see our utility bills increase and what protections for the environment and human health are being considered what third party review is being performed and what if those considerations aren't enough what happens when our community gets sick when our already heavily burdened health care system is unable to keep up with the increase in asthma and heart disease and cancer and what happens with the lawsuit that follows because as we all know an emerging environmental concern is a lawsuit on the horizon what then and maybe these questions have been considered it sounds like you have more information than was originally presented to us and if that's the case then great but i don't know because that information has not yet been adequately communicated to us now i don't expect everyone to become a tree-hugging hippie i don't think that's realistic but i ask that we think of people like my grandma who over the last decade of her life had such severe asthma that she was unable to get the mail at the end of her own driveway that is how bad lancaster county's air quality is i look forward to the forthcoming information that you promised and in addition with the developer i'd also like to add that i'd like to meet with the proposed tenants i want to make sure that they understand that by building here they have the same obligation as you or i do to protect this community i yield my time thank you mr harris our
next speaker next speaker is Ann Torres good evening hi my name is Ann Torres I live in lettuce but I work in Lancaster years back my friend had a baby through IVF they finally had their baby but over time they noticed that he was having issues breathing in and out of hospitals extensive stays but no answers just constant treatment to keep him alive and breathing and it's heartbreaking to see a child who was very healthy in every other way confined to a hospital bed for too much of his life. I remember the day she came to me and said, Ann, we'll probably need to move. He can't breathe here. It's the air. As the move never came to fruition, he saw more hospital visits throughout his childhood. He is nine now. He is relatively stable except for the constant struggle of allergies and asthma. If he gets sick, like the common cold, there's a good chance that he ends up hospitalized. Is this the life, the future we want for our children? Lancaster already ranks 22nd for the worst air quality in the nation air pollutants cause roughly 200 000 premature deaths yearly in the u.s now this should go without saying but no one should be dying from breathing the air this these electricity consuming fossil fuel power ai data centers will accelerate that pollution massively in pa from 2024 to 2025 there has been a 174 percent increase in electric use due to these AI data centers. To the tune of $9 billion, a cost that is spread to you and me because AI data centers, while they get to privatize their profits, they get to socialize their operational costs. In areas of high data center growth, consumers can expect to see an additional estimated $450 added to their yearly electric costs. Oh, and not only do we help to pay to keep these centers running, but these companies are getting taxes tax exemptions in 36 states including pa to qualify for these exemptions they must spend 75 million on their investment property and guarantee at least 25 jobs 25 jobs what a low bar an insult to the community and trade for our health this exemption guarantees that they do not have to pay sales tax on the very costly vital tech equipment that they need to build these centers which of course means pa loses millions every time these centers are built millions that could go into to healthcare, housing, and other social safety nets that we are quickly losing. In Indiana, an Amazon data center promised to rate 1,000 new jobs. They failed to mention that 60% of those jobs would be temporary construction, and the other 40% could only be fulfilled when they completed their total project of 16 total data centers. So as AI data centers steamroll this country, this state, this county, quickly outpacing any regulation in their industry, please ask yourself, what are you, Shapiro, McCormick, willing to trade for short-term monetary investments. A child's future? This cannot happen. Lancaster cannot let this happen. Thank you. Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker.
Our next speaker is Frank Arcolio.
Arcolio.
Good evening, Mr. Arcolio.
Hi, thank you. Frank Arcolio, Old Trinity Place. It's only a circle, so one block. All the other speakers have dwelt on all the bad aspects of having a data center, the gluttonous use of electricity, the gluttonous use of water, or if you're air cooling it, more gluttonous use of electricity, and the lack of jobs that eventually come out no matter what they promise. But I'm gonna ask the big Watergate question today. What did you know and when did you know it? We only found out on Friday. But guess what? there was a $130 million investment purchase in February. How come we're just finding out about this now? The paper said when that investment was made, it was made eyed for data centers. Did you not notice? You know, I've been in business and in consulting for nearly 50 years. There is no one that I've ever met who wants to go spend $130 million speculatively without knowing that that investment was gonna yield a return, without knowing that it was gonna be just okay with everyone to put a data center here. And so we find out about it on July 18th. None of you who found out before that raised any qualms, talked to anyone, talked to the public about what it might do to us. And now, guess what? We're told, it's too late to do anything. Oh, what a shame. If you had started in February, we could have done a lot. Do you think we wouldn't notice? Do you think we wouldn't care? Do you think we have to play cat and mouse with you to check up on you, to make sure that you're doing your job? what we want is for you to stop this damn data center right now we want control by the city over such properties they are not warehouses trust me on that we need you to do the kinds of zoning amendments that have been presented here tonight that guarantee and the regulations need to guarantee water use electricity use and to make sure that any other environmental impact is dealt with not by their assurances but by third party uh objective people even manor township has this why can't lancaster city i think somebody's been had either you guys have been had or we've been had but it's not good for lancaster county thank you thank you sir
I want to thank the members of the public for coming out tonight and speaking to council as I mentioned before this is new information to many of us despite insinuations and I want to also assure you that council is committed to keeping the public informed as updates are provided on all matters including any public engagement opportunities that would be before this body or any other opportunity to do so so thank you very much for that we will proceed with the next item on our meeting agenda this evening i will if anyone needs to step out give you a moment to do so but otherwise we will keep going and again thank you very much for your comments this evening the next item on our agenda is reports requested by council that is the capital budget public hearing and i know that we'll have a presentation members of council you were sent a presentation earlier this evening so that should be in your email and we have i believe directors campbell and members of the public works team that will be presenting you can join us right here all right mr harris confirming that the uh that will be displayed on the screen momentarily working on it okay great we'll take a brief pause as we work on technology and get set up
council while uh council president if i may while we're getting the technology situated mayor srachi um i i want to just acknowledge the work of the department of public works in preparing for council the first ever capital plan to be presented this is one of the requirements that
was born the wireless mics are a little finicky we're um we're trying okay so as i was saying
this capital plan which director Campbell and his team are going to discuss tonight is part of is an outcome of the adoption of the home rule charter that requires council to be presented on an annual basis the capital plan in its totality and so you will hear tonight uh related to our storm water our our general fund which includes our parks active transportation and roads as well as our water and sewer systems and i'm really want to just thank um director steve campbell uh for his leadership in bringing this across the finish line along with members of his team i also want to give an acknowledgement to david kapach for helping to translate all of the data into a new software application that we are using that will be able to provide the kind of information that council needs to make financial decisions as it relates to our future investments in our capital infrastructure
and with that um turn it back thank you very much mayor sirachi uh director campbell team good evening and thank you for being here i'm yes and we're uh we'll just as we learned at our last committee meeting we try to have one of those on at a time so thank you well thank you very much
for the opportunity to formally present the capital budget in the form of the capital investment program for fiscal years 2026 through 2030 as per the home rule charter we must submit a capital budget annually by june of each year which we did on june 24th of last month with a list of projects published on june 30th in this presentation we are reminding you of the drivers of the capital budget and we will be highlighting most of the large projects within the budget our esteemed deputy directors will present their respective portfolios and you should ask them any questions that come to mind regarding the work in their purview and as noted in the earlier presentations it is an opportunity for you to clarify how you would like this information presented in the future director Tina Campbell will be available to refresh and update you as to how we we establish estimated costs, et cetera, if necessary and as you have questions. Next slide, please. In the aggregate, this is a graphic of the 2026 to 2030 CIP over the next five years of just over $300 million. You'll note that the largest investments are in water at 36% or $108 million, wastewater at 31 percent or 94 million dollars both of those represent two-thirds of the cip over the next five years and deputy director christine volke hilditch will describe the drivers and the projects that make up that portfolio of projects the remaining third is made up of streets at 18 or 54 million dollars and parks and public works administration work each at five percent at approximately 15.5 million dollars each deputy director cindy mccormick and and i will present and describe that work the balance of that third is in stormwater just under five percent at approximately 13.6 million dollars and deputy director molly dagger will describe that work next slide this just presents the work described by enterprise fund where parks streets and public works administration comprise the general fund stormwater is its own enterprise fund and water and wastewater respectively are separate enterprise funds next slide we'll start with parks and streets so i will turn it over to deputy director of public right-of-way and the city engineer cindy mccormick thank you director campbell
if you go to the next slide so these are our main investment drivers I would say related to the public right-of-way we have and these are these plans generally guide the investments that we're making in each of these areas so we have the parks master plan which was adopted last year this is identifying a lot of our priorities related to renovating our parks and any other amenities or services that the city may need related to parks we have our vision zero and traffic safety plan this is where we are prioritizing traffic roadway improvements to the vision zero is that we have zero fatal and serious injury crashes within the city so that is our goal and that's what we strive towards so that's making sure that we're focusing our resources on the most dangerous locations then we have our active transportation plan and this is identifying transportation facilities that provide alternative modes of travel so rather than relying on the car to get everywhere we're trying to provide infrastructure for bicyclists pedestrians other modes so that they have options to feel safe when they're traveling throughout the city I would say a lot of our projects we they sort of overlap with the vision zero and active transportation where we're trying while we're providing that active transportation we're also making sure that we're improving safety for all users so not just the pedestrians and bicyclists and then finally maintaining our infrastructure so you know our traffic signals paving our streets those kind of improvements that need to be made to maintain that surface infrastructure and again anytime that we're doing any of those types of projects we're looking to see how we can improve safety for the people using them so the um so yeah a lot of our investment includes sort of baselines of making investments in each of these areas but then also as additional initiatives might come along they are added as well next slide so the first slide and i this is very busy so understand if we can't get through necessarily all of it but we'll focus on our parks planning um and these are ordered in the amount of investment so the highest investment is are located at the top but i may jump around a little bit related to this so just from our parks master plan you know we identified three parks that were sort of the highest need located in the southeast they were joe jackson tot lot the yule gantz playground and south end park so we have been able to prioritize those parks and actually joe jackson and yule gantz have just gone out we'll be going out to bid i think tomorrow as we have completed the design for that and are ready to get that towards construction we're also working on design related to the south end park as well and then just focusing on some another the other project that's sort of in construction or will be soon if you go down the list to the conestoga pines connection that is a connection where we're connecting the walnut street fishing area to the conestoga pines park so creating a path between the two crossing the river and getting over to conestoga pines park so that is actually up to bid now as well so those are projects that are currently or will be in construction soon um and then just sort of going through identifying what our next priorities are related to planning and what parks need to be improved next we have reservoir park which would you know that's a very large park for us so that will require planning and then it has a large construction cost that we're anticipating and i guess this is again this is just sort of an estimate because we haven't really gone through the whole process of what exactly the scope of work will be but given the size we anticipate it will be a large project other planning projects include we've talked about a municipal pool that's another area where the pool currently at conestoga pines park is um in starting to become in disrepair and you know based on the location um we may be looking we may want we want to look at if there are alternative locations so that's one of the areas where we're starting to look at planning for those other areas include the duke street mall the linear park so that 50 foot wide park that travels along south duke street we're making improvements along south duke street and that project i'll talk about a little bit later but we're also wanting to identify improvements to make activate the duke street mall area as well and then are there so then also we have culleton park phase two which was a building that the city is currently using that was a that was acquired adjacent to culleton park that the city is currently using as the salt shed but the future plans could include additional park amenities uh there as well so these are projects that we're looking at um planning over the next five years starting the planning and even some could potentially go to construction um do we want
to ask i'd like to just i'd like to just make it clear what what the columns are reading black on red is a is a difficult visual and i apologize for that but the first five the first column the column on the left is the description of the project the next columns are fiscal 26 fiscal 27 fiscal 28 fiscal 29 and fiscal 30 culminating in a total for the project which is in bold in almost in the middle of the sheet the next column is the column that indicates what is already funded or known to be funded the next column is what is anticipated for the 2025 bond issue. The next column is the column of funds that have already been granted towards these projects. The next column is a column for other sources of funding. They may not be bond, may not be grants, it might be something else a little bit different. The second to last column is the 2028 bond, so that's looking three years out at an anticipated additional bond on a three-year cycle. And last but certainly not least is the column called unfunded which recognizes that there may still be work to be done to find the funding for this project and in general if we do not find that funding in the time that it is needed we will do one of two or three things we will either look seek to see if that can be added to the fiscal 20 the 2028 bond we will look to possibly defer the project or we would look to d uh to de-scope or reduce the scope of that project to stay within the funds and in the budget we've got we already have that's the that's the sequence of the columns that you'll see as you
go forward for all of these presentations thank you for that dr campbell i appreciate it a quick question that may help provide context here the grant column are grants that we have we know we have received only okay and uh not to say there won't be additional grants in the future and then i also want to kind of put a fine point on the fact that this is a plan that spans until fiscal year 2030 and we're going to be looking at it again every year so these columns will come up again and again and again to benchmark and also update us on changes challenges opportunities
every single year absolutely we're trying to build that culture of knowledge of how to read this kind of a capital budget we're asking if there's things that you need presented in a slightly different way to make it clearer for you clearer for the public to understand but also to recognize that you'll be seeing the same things year after year but we'll be revisiting the entire
program as the time moves forward thank you um i'll pause if counselors have anything additional
this point and we'll continue so this slide is highlighting um basically what we're calling the streets or the public right-of-way projects as you can see there are many there and again this is identifying projects related to vision zero related to active transportation and then just maintenance of our existing infrastructure in general um and you know a lot of the projects that we end up progressing are ones that we are able to find some matching grant funds for so that's often a driver as to what we're trying to progress our projects that we have a high level of confidence that we would be able to obtain grant funding so i'll start at the top we have our safe streets for all projects and this is related to the federal highway grant that we received to implement our vision zero plan so the grant is worth 12.6 million dollars with a 15 million dollar total i will say that some of these you know when i mentioned the 12.6 million this starts in 2026 so it's not accounting for funds that have been expended in 2025. so we are you know these include some supplemental studies like looking at the conversion of our one-way streets one-way streets to two-way just implementing roadway improvement projects on our high injury network identifying improvements around schools that to help you know kids traveling to and from school just to improve the safety in those areas we are focusing on initially Carter McCray and the McCaskey campus so and then just to give a plug to we have an open house next it's on the 30th I believe it's next Thursday that will be our first open house related to vision zero and our safe streets for all projects so it's going to be an all-day drop-in session at the library so I encourage everyone to come and stop and see in more detail the work that we're doing on that project next is our water street bike boulevard project where we're adding adding bike facilities not adding but using and making improvements along water street from harrisburg ave to fairview for a bike boulevard this includes a couple off-road sections and this is quite a large project but we do have a large amount of grant funding that is funding that project as well so that should be happening starting construction hopefully next year the next project is the northeast greenway walkway boardwalk project this is a project connecting the operation center at riverside avenue to the walnut street fishing area which would then connect to the conestoga pine park connection that i just spoke about earlier so that's another project and again we have significant grant funding related to that project and just to talk a couple about some of the traffics we have quite a few traffic signal projects we the state offers grant funding that allows us to take advantage of that almost every year so we're wanting to make sure that we're using that resource to upgrade our traffic signals there are a couple other traffic signal projects noted on here which I won't go into a lot of detail on but you can see them listed Chesapeake and Broad bike facilities we're looking at adding bike facilities on that stretch of roadway from Queen Street all the way to King Street so that will be a significant addition and we are fortunate enough to have PennDOT will be paying for the paving of that street so that's another great opportunity there and then I will also highlight Church Street improvements and another project where PennDOT is assisting we are looking we will be taking away one lane of that three lane section to two lanes and then also making like side path improvements as well and then there are also Ann and Juniata Ann is on our high injury network so that is an another project where we're trying to improve safety around some of the school campuses related to that and then I will jump to South Duke Street that is a project that will be going to construction that has been awarded to a contractor so that will be starting construction this fall and that is adding back in diagonal parking along Duke Street and a side path so I think I'm gonna stop there unless anyone has any more specific questions I know there's a lot of projects here thank you just one quick
question regarding the grant funding so understanding that we're anticipating some of those funding opportunities are there any risks of losing that on some based on some of the proposals at the state right now I am not aware of any
that we would be at risk of losing at this point all the grants that are shown there we're under contract for so I don't anticipate any change there thank
you. Thank you. That's our men.
Thank you, Council President. Thank you, President. And thank you. This is very informative. In regards to some of the unfunded allocations for multiple of the projects, and kind of piggybacking off Councillor Royals question, you know, if we are not seeing those get funded year over year, can we add that to the 2028 bond? It's like next year and the projection or I guess also as director Campbell mentioned like when would we decide okay like we may need to pause this project or defer this project if we don't see it move out of that unfunded column yeah I mean a lot of the projects
we're looking at planning you know initially so spending some money on design so that we can sort of you know we identify the scope and then pursuing the funding so a lot of times we'll start an initial design but we won't get into the final design until we have that funding secured so it's sort of yes as director Campbell mentioned we just need to evaluate it year by year and then you know and make sure that that's still the priority and you know how we want to move forward with it we also sometimes we'll look at how we can reduce the scope um you know based on a lot of times we'll get grant awards that are less than what we ask for so we have to adjust as as more information becomes available to us if i may add to that as
well this is one of the advantages of having a long-term capital plan this is the first time we've been able to look as far as 30 to 32 years in advance not as a not as a guarantee that that's will happen on those particular years but to anticipate when certain infrastructure needs to be replaced when certain infrastructure needs to be upgraded or as technology changes etc it does a lot as cindy had indicated we would be doing this assessment on an annual basis to reconfirm the level of funding that we have that's available and and would reflect if anything has changed costs might rise availability of materials may change all of that needs to be managed it on on a rolling basis so this is gives us an opportunity and you is an opportunity as well to see what the challenges are and to help us
make some of those decisions yes thank you and I really do appreciate this level of financial planning I have a capital plan at the hotel I manage so know it really excites me to see that you know each individual project has you know the allocations year over year so i really appreciate you and your team's efforts with that thank you anything else
from council before we proceed thank you okay thank you next slide please and now we'll turn over to the construction and operations division which is under matt metzler who was not able to to join us this evening. He's the Deputy Director of Construction and Operations, and will be describing the drivers and projects within the Public Works, what we call the Public Works Administration portion. Next slide. So the basic investment drivers include three base, for, I'm sorry.
I don't know why, but whenever the papers are very close to these mics, I don't know what sort of like Bluetooth technology working with here but i'm just electric that's okay it's you it's your electric personality
thank you so there for for the the next five years or so these are the key drivers for us the first two are drivers not just for these next five years but ongoing facilities and maintenance operations and efficiency and the welcome center renovation which i'll talk about a little bit more in terms of maintaining our parks and public property we have 26 public parks and recreational areas five wading pools one full-size pool eight major operational facilities ten public restrooms and we plan and replace a plan and replacement schedule based on our facilities condition assessment that we put in place back in 2022 where we were able to do a facility condition assessment of all of our built what we call our vertical vertical construction including the parts we're looking for opportunities for operational efficiencies as well which includes combining smaller satellite offices and operations into centralized locations for efficiency economics of scale public convenience and reduction in time and fuel and combining similar functions across bureaus and departments under one roof such as archiving equipment storage vehicle storage and maintenance warehousing and expanding capabilities and reducing costs and certainly one jewel in the crown of lancaster city assets the welcome center renovation the centralized hub for implementing key goals identified in the tourism master plan and implementing technology and focused advertising on realizing lancaster as a tourist destination next slide so similar to what cindy had done i'll be going through several of the larger projects related to public works administration construction and operations the first one on this on the sheet is the operations center what we're calling the operations center expansion it's consolidation of functions including equipment storage warehousing archives etc at this particular moment we don't have the ideal location for such but we recognize that we have facilities scattered throughout the city and that makes us significantly less efficient and makes it difficult to maintain certain of our equipment so we are looking looking at opportunities to consolidate if we do not find the type of site that we're looking for there actually is a space on part of one of our existing sites that might be able to accommodate part of that work the next is the capital projects the next is capital projects outlays for facility condition assessments as i had indicated the 2022 facility condition assessments gives an exhausting an exhaustive list of the assets whether they're windows doors floors, foundations, roofs, equipment, appliances, and things like that, that indicate the remaining useful life of those particular assets, allow us to more predictively and more accurately determine what needs to be replaced and when it needs to be replaced, and the relative costs for that. In the past, I think we've done a very, very good job of identifying or anticipating what the needs were but it was not based on a lot of science if you will we would walk each of the facilities and say we have eight eight of the twenty eight of the forty buildings windows are broken it's time to replace the windows rather than perhaps being able to do the calculus that says it's going to be less expensive to replace those eight windows right now and wait until the remaining use for life later so we are in the very enviable enviable position that many of our facilities are in very good shape and it also means we have we now have the tools to more accurately and more judiciously spend rather than spend because we fear that something may fail the next is on-site solar generation currently unfunded to identify and implement solar on the roofs of sites or existing city buildings we currently spend approximately approaching three million dollars annually on costs for power and electric almost 20 percent of which could be generated by solar and thus see a return in as little as eight years this also goes towards our climate action plan efforts so part of the goal would be to work with with solar and energy brokers and molly may be able to speak to a little a little bit more on how to utilize the roofs of buildings that are structurally appropriate for such to add solar and therefore reduce our our energy costs the salt shed cindy had mentioned that we need to be able to consolidate a single location for efficiency and convenience saving precious moments in snow removal but also releasing for other more public uses the site and sites that we currently use for salt storage the welcome center renovation and i i neglected to indicate but you can see the numbers up above the operation center we're guesstimating will be about approximately 6.9 million dollars over the course of several years the capital projects outlay we're looking at approximately 750 000 dollars annually to look at the work that needs to be revisited from the facility condition assessment that may increase and drop depending on the uh the the remaining useful life of certain of the assets the on-site solar generation we estimate for the roofs that we believe we can do this on approximately 2.5 million dollars the salt shed approximately 1.5 million dollars and then the welcome center renovation approximately 1.5 million dollars built in the late night 1790s it was built as a public office house and likely the original city hall the building now serves as lancaster city's welcome center and will be upgraded and restored to implement key goals identified in the tourism master plan including offices meeting spaces and display and storytelling two other areas where we need specific work are the lancaster police station roof needs to be replaced that building is more than 20 years about 20 years old now i forget exactly how old but it is it is the roof has reached the end of its of its designed useful life and so it needs to be replaced and then last but certainly not least in this particular stretch the citywide telephone platform replacement i was not sorry it's not last citywide telephone platform replacement in aid of upgrading our telephone system at 184 thousand dollars or about sixty four thousand dollars sixty two thousand dollars per year for that upgrade city hall facade cleaning and sealing at to the tune of fifty thousand dollars of the building we are we are sitting in right now the facade requires cleaning some modest repair and sealing to better preserve the exterior of the building and therefore make it less expensive to maintain and certainly last but certainly not least for many who are inhabit the building the recycling center at 850 New Holland Avenue where it needs a new boiler the people who are serving us to deal with our recycling are freezing their blanks off because of the inadequacy of the existing system next slide so just in quick summary this summarizes the subsets of the general front fund CIP note that about 64 million of the 85 million dollars is funded which leaves about 20 million 20 almost 21 million unfunded more than 50 percent of the general fund cip is from grants and other sources we anticipate 4.2 million input from the 2028 bond and otherwise we will continue as we mentioned before to seek grants for the balance and we're not successful we will either look to increase the ask from the 2028 bond or reduce scope for these otherwise necessary investments or, in an even worse case scenario, defer those projects. Before going into stormwater, which is the next enterprise fund, are there any questions regarding either construction and operations or anything within the general fund?
Thank you, Director Campbell. Counselors, anything before the next section?
Thank you. Continue. Okay. So I will now let's turn to the stormwater CIP. which deputy director Molly Digger will outline for us Molly sorry everybody can
you switch just don't leave that one off yep we've angered the Bluetooth microphone gods don't use that one and Cindy don't forget just push it away let's try that one now thank you okay okay sorry about that everybody even
more electric i think more electric thank you director campbell uh next slide please we'll show the pretty rain garden for a moment and then we can advance to the next slide so the city's five-year capital plan that i present to you this evening for the stormwater fund prioritizes strategic investments that deliver multiple benefits environmental economic and community-wide lancaster is a national leader in green infrastructure using our rain gardens our tree trenches our green roofs our permeable pavements to manage storm water this is well embedded in our long-term planning and i'll go through some examples of that on the next slide but this is transforming how we manage water in a way that also serves our climate resilience goals and our neighborhood revitalization so these practices are reducing flooding improving water quality air quality supporting our pollinators cooling our neighborhoods and making our city more beautiful and livable we've been doing green infrastructure for so long here in lancaster that while many of our systems are performing as designed or over performing it is time for us to be planning strategically for the uh as part of the long-term operation and maintenance to be allocating some of our capital funds to more substantial corrective actions to some of our assets to ensure the continued long-term success we've built a strong track record our projects are strategically implemented to reduce combined sewer overflows that i'm sure christine will touch on later via our long-term control plan and also to meet the state's permitting requirements in our non-combined parts of the city known as the municipal separate storm sewer system or the ms4 areas next slide please similar format the first half of the slide that you see shows the different allocations from 2026 through 2030 and then some some of the funding mechanisms on the right hand side uh with respect to some of those regulatory uh obligations that i mentioned before i'm going to jump around a little bit these are again in order in which from largest to to smallest but i wanted to just on the long-term control plan and on our ms4 obligations highlight first the ari projects that you see that's the asset renewal inventory projects this is an acronym that we're using in our long-term control planning but this is these are basically the green infrastructure projects that the city is committed to in our combined sewer system areas planning efforts in 2028 will dictate what those are and what those will be because as you'll see a lot of our initiatives are combined with other city initiatives as well so that ari project is directly for those combined sewer system areas likewise the ms4 collection system upgrades that's those are the separate sewer system areas this could be new inlets or new piping to alleviate flooding and to improve roadway conditions and safety improvements this could also be green infrastructure such as the improvements that were made at longs park in order to meet those permitting obligations as well one of the most important things that i wanted to show though is one of the most one of the city's most effective strategies is bundling these stormwater improvements with other capital improvements so you'll notice a common thread through the list the stormwater bureau looks at green infrastructure potential in the paving plan the city's vision zero and safe streets for all initiatives which is why you'll see things like reservoir park in the stormwater cip as well just to note there is going to be green infrastructure at joe jackson yule gantz and south end the parks that cindy highlighted earlier and and so we do we strategically incorporate green infrastructure and as many of these projects as possible other collaborative efforts that you see on this list include the stormwater costs for capital improvements they might not be green infrastructure but they will have important stormwater benefit and again alleviating flooding improving conditions in our in our streets and in our community the operations center facility stormwater contribution there will be some stormwater improvements that happens through those consolidated and expansion opportunities that steve touched on as well as green infrastructure at the new bay street community garden which will we hope to begin planning next year with implementation as early as 2027. so this integrated approach stretches every dollar load lowers total project costs and minimizes disruption to residents when we can be tackling certain construction or multiple construction efforts at the same time so thanks for bearing with me i know i'm bouncing around a lot the only two items that i hadn't specifically mentioned on this list are the corrective actions the green infrastructure corrective actions and that's what i had alluded to before we are putting sort of a slightly increased placeholder in future years to account for the fact that as we grow our green infrastructure program and as these systems age we do want to be allocating funding for the renewal of those green infrastructure assets that we have and then last but certainly not least is the trees for people implementation which will use a combination of federal funds and the 2022 stormwater bond funding for the urban forest reset this is under construction right now around our city streets and will continue on in through the next few years we presented a little bit about the urban forestry program to council earlier this year but again we're creating a healthier more robust tree canopy along the city streets this tackles a number of stormwater related goals we think that trees are the city's best green infrastructure as well as other climate climate resiliency goals as well so over the next five years residents will see projects in more parks more neighborhoods and more public spaces and again to manage stormwater and to uh to improve our daily life through those other benefits that i mentioned before we oh sure sure yes questions about stormwater projects
i do have a question uh the lines for the ms4 collection system and the um there's another line i'm sorry and the uh oh i see the green infrastructure correct corrective action yes um actually no just the ms4 system line so that's the same number repeated year over year i'm assuming there were some assumptions made about just like average cost can you talk a little bit more about what those could be and then also i see it's in the
the unfunded category can you talk a little bit more about that yes um there were some assumptions made and this is a combination of upgrades that we might need to make in our separate sewer areas these this is a placeholder because we don't know yet what those might be the other thing the other sort of big placeholder and the reason that it's unfunded is because the city is actually in compliance and has met all of its current ms4 permit project requirements it was called a pollutant reduction plan and the city has fulfilled those obligations the state is revising the permit requirements for the ms4 permit but it has administratively extended the permit for at least another 12 months and we we do not know yet what the permit obligations will be so we don't know yet what we will spend or what or where we will target those funds yet exactly when yeah or exactly when and so what we've done is is made an educated guess based on the money that was spent in the last permit cycle and we were very successful with grant funding and other types of funds penvest loans things like that for some of those projects so we are confident that once we know what those permit obligations will be we can be updating those uh numbers and hopefully have much less in the unfunded category to present to council next year that makes sense
that we will be able to match them with funding sources as we get a little bit more defined yep thank you uh counselors anything on this one before we proceed councilor hirsch thank you
council president just had a brief question on the trees for people program and i understand that that's going forward over the next couple years into 2028 can you just reiterate what the what the goal is as far as like number of trees planted over the next three years and then if you happen to have it available what progress has been made thus far on said goals
sure um i'm trying to do some fast math in my head here i know that through a half a million dollars in arpa funding that the city received through the lancaster clean water partners we are installing about 380 new street trees this year we are i think we're about halfway through that target so probably a little under 200 trees were planted in the spring and then the rest will be fall planting there's some concrete work associated with that project happening now so that will wrap up by the end of this year and then with the other with the other federal funds that we received from the U.S. Forest Service we are targeting about which we're still finalizing the numbers we were looking at trying to find upwards of 400 new street tree wells around the city and then either conducting restorative pruning to bring trees that were in fair condition back up to an acceptable level of health tree health and then where that wasn't appropriate removing and replacing trees as part of that effort so that could be another upwards of two to three hundred new trees through that effort as well so it would be 450 plus 380 plus two to three hundred more thank you yeah counselors
anything additional on this slide so far so good that was the okay one okay next
we're going to turn to utilities enterprise funds will be which will be outlined by deputy director of both wastewater and water utilities Christine
Volke Hilditch next slide please so we're gonna start with the wastewater treatment plant our plants located off New Danville Pike right outside the city it has a capacity of 32 million gallons a day on a good day dry weather we may be running about 18 million gallons a day when it rains our flows go up to 50 million gallons a day so you can see by the picture there's a lot of facilities there's a lot of components in addition to the plant we also have seven pump stations that pump wastewater to the plant wastewater also comes in through gravity to this to the plant and we also maintain over hundreds of force maine and gravity sore within the system so when we go through our capital plan you can see that it's a significant investment to treat water and on this end we're treating we're reclaiming waste water and putting it back into the next slide so our drivers are our infrastructure and regulatory requirements as you've heard over the years we have a judicial consent decree with the epa and the dep to address our combined sewer overflows and we're required to develop a long-term control plan we've submitted an alternatives analysis and our next regulatory requirement is in september to submit the long term control plan the regulatory drivers in wastewater are significant we are now being regulated with a new npdes permit which is the permit that allows us to discharge into the conestoga river that has additional requirements most important is the start of monitoring for the forever chemicals you've heard a lot about those in the news and we'll be talking a little bit more about them in our water system so when we talk about not knowing what the future holds and that we will be revising this capital plan year over year our regulatory drivers will be what affects In Pennsylvania, we are still allowed to land-apply the solids generated in the wastewater treatment process. We do this also under permit, and in several states throughout the nation, that practice is being eliminated. So our concern as a driver for the future is that we generate less biosolids. we are looking at significant infrastructure spending for digestion anaerobic digestion which will allow us to both reduce the amount of solids that we have to dispose of as well as give us opportunities in energy generation one of the things that the current federal regulations allow is the ability to generate credits for for developing green gas an anaerobic digester generates methane and that methane can be reused on the grid on the on the gas grid so we're trying to position ourselves for less expenses although debt will increase we'll be looking at less costs for disposal over the past ten years we've seen our disposal costs double you know we're over two million dollars now for disposal costs for for sludge next slide please within our capital projects we have funding for what we call our municipal partners so the plant takes in wastewater from the lancaster area sewer authority from the suburban air area sewer authority from missing one leola as well as east lampeter sewer authority so several other municipal partners contribute to capital projects at the wastewater plant as well as the stations the pump stations so depending on the use in terms of their flow contribution will drive how much they contribute to the capital projects so in our in our project information we have what the city will be spending as well as some of these will be contributed by other funding sources we'll start with anaerobic digestion which is to install dryers and tanks that will reduce the amount of sludge that we generate our next project is a secondary clarifier clarifiers settle the solids that are generated in the process we'll be adding a sixth clarifier for additional treatment capacity and resiliency the next project is the in is the rehabilitation of an interceptor from the that feeds the conestoga gardens pumping station following that is the water street sewer separation project we'll be separating a combined sewer system which will help reduce our combined sewer overflows we're adding a scrubber in our chlorination facilities this is for safety and resiliency so that we can address any issues with chlorine the north primary clarifier rehabilitation is for a new equipment within those tanks new flights scrapers that will help settle the sludge south screening head works is for new screens these screen the wastewater as it comes into the plant the collection systems improvement is a placeholder for any issues that occur within the collection system and we'll see this as a placeholder year over year this project allows us to line and replace gravity source within the system the south primary clara fire rehabilitation very similar to the north project we are replacing equipment within the tanks rehabilitating the concrete as part of that project broad street is another sewer separation project next slide i'm sorry so on the second page we have structural repair and piping system upgrades some of our piping and the plant property is from the 1930s 1980s so we'll be looking at replacing key pipes we've had some leaks over the years so this is a general rehabilitation project of all the piping our motor control center replacement is in the control building we'll be replacing switch gear within that building the north pump station cso outfall project is to rehabilitate the clay street outfall this is up near the mccaskey campus the sort the system is about 100 years old so we'll be structurally reinforcing the the sore outfall and the piping that that leads to that outfall um the south train diversion is for chlorination improvements on our cso outfall 100 our combined outfall we are rebuilding four belt filter presses and two discharge conveyors this is in our solids processing and the presses dewater the sludge and the conveyors take it out to the trucks for disposal the chlorine contact upgrade is for structural repairs in our chlorine contact tanks the next project is site paving we have a significant large site and we're we're repainting it and the last one is the lime stabilization is to replace a the bio bio filters odor control system media thank you so it's a lot of projects over five years mainly because of the infrastructure so one of our drivers as i said is the regulatory requirements you will note in this particular list of projects we do not have major long-term control plan projects that is because our strategy when we're putting in our alternative analysis is to concentrate on infrastructure and wastewater and more importantly the drivers in water so we'll be spending a lot of money on water i know this is bad but water is is even more because of the regulatory drivers so we are going to propose to the epa that we will first spend money in the water system for compliance and we will not start spending on the cso's other than some of the sewer separation projects and the gi projects that molly mentioned but the the rest of the spending would be out in probably 2037. we're spending 10 years spending in water and then we'll start spending in sewer other than what we're talking about is the the normal repair and replacement of the infrastructure before we proceed
i have two questions the first is the impacts of those separation projects water street sewer separation and then there was there was others there overall what is the impact of those projects i know you mentioned focusing on the water first but is that a significant or an insignificant impact if you could kind of just talk about it in general terms i'm going to refer that to molly
because she's going to be managing the project that sewer is going to be paying for it okay
yes so the water street sewer separation will be built ahead of the water street bike boulevard project that cindy spoke about these this will remove approximately 40 acres of impervious drainage that is today going into the angle side sewer shed which is the city's largest combined sewer system and at a relatively cost efficient manner projected costs are about i just looked at this yesterday 250 000 per acre which is a little bit less than what our green infrastructure costs again we are there are some efficiencies efficiencies in the fact that we're collaborating with other users and that there was a a portion along fairview that was separated um several decades decades ago but was just then tied back into the combined sewer system so we'll be disconnecting that broad street is less it's about nine acres but then we will have the opportunity to disconnect from the north basin and into infrastructure that the city actually already built under the wickersham turf fields under the mccaskey campus yes and then we'll have the opportunity to daylight that storm water into groff's run which the city invested in a stream restoration project a number of years ago so it will bring back some base flow and we're already collaborating with the school district to incorporate some environmental opportunities
there as well thank you for that context that's exactly the kind of kind of connection i was hoping to make with that question and then my second question is um the last line on the first uh slide the last one on the list annual escrow special and emergency improvements so obviously we have to put something aside and plan for rainy days no pun intended rainy days um lots of rainy days rainy days in terms of like when things happen that we don't plan for has this number that we've chosen a half a million dollars annually does that generally line up with about how much we typically spend on these sort of emergency improvements that come up
no um it is a placeholder okay um we contribute um a little less than 250 000 and so do the partners okay we put it in escrow and we tap it as needed so it may be a small planned project like we buy a new mixer in the aeration system a small roof repair or it may be because something broke okay so it is a placeholder we've been doing it for the last maybe eight years it's been working pretty well sometimes we even defer like every year but maybe it's every 14 months or maybe we have to fund every eight months but we we fund it we plan for it on a frequency of an annual contribution
thank you for that and i appreciate the good stewardship of our systems any additional questions from council on these two slides oh I'm sorry
counselor colleagues Thank You madam president and thank you for the presentation and I'm not sure who would answer this question and how is the department working to minimize the cost of those projects we can we
competitively bid all of our projects we always ask the engineers to do a cost estimate so we can determine whether we are in budget you know from estimates we might have done with you know during the design process so our biggest driver is competitive bidding so that you're you're putting together a good set of plans and specifications that you can put out we do our bidding on the platform called pen bid so it's widely advertised within the state so i think the most important thing is to have good plans and specifications so that your contractors know exactly what you want to minimize your changeovers and for any
unforeseen circumstance thank you thank you madam president thank you council royal maybe this
question is too soon for tonight um but curious about capacity and project management for a lot of these projects um there's a lot going on especially in 26 and 27. what does capacity look like on the teams as well as what does project management look like in sequencing these projects just kind of thinking about construction thinking about resident experience how does that play a factor into some of these some of the timeline for for a lot of these
projects when we look at um you know in terms of internal external capacity our design work is done with outside engineers managed with inside engineers the largest project will be the digester project and the phasing of that will also be looked at as what our as our debt you know changes because that'll be a significant borrowing we will be at least two years plus in design and probably three to four years in construction so it'll be a study project that will go on long term the clarifier I thought we'd already be under design we had had some funding set aside in previous bond funds and ended up reconfiguring projects because of the time it's taking to buy the land we have to buy a little sliver of land from PP&L to put the clarifier in the northern part of the plant that has taken significant time they're now in PUC approval for selling that little piece of land to us as another municipal entity and then we have to go through a land development process with Lancaster counter. So I'm a little concerned on when we actually can start more right now than than the capacity issue, mainly because a lot of our projects on this are at the plant. So our in house engineer can keep an eye on them. But we will also have inspectors inspectors from the consulting you know, I'm sorry, we will have inspectors from the consulting engineer who help manage the day-to-day so we do have and we do access outside help on a slightly different note
i think it is impressive just yeah the amount of projects that you're being uh that are being discussed this evening um you know we do have a lot of expertise within dpw and and city staff i also am very um pleased with the collaboration that happens between uh divisions in the city as well i know you know we have a lot of projects that are either out to bid or going out to construction and there's a lot of expertise in all three division in all four divisions but when we're looking at a stormwater project we rely on one of the public works engineers who is an expert in procurement and we will rely on a wastewater project manager you know on some of these sewer separation projects and so we really do i think work well together to sort of lighten the load a bit and we are all busy and if i could just add one
last thing we do on an annual basis in the in the operations budget budget for the staff we don't always fill fill or fulfill all those all those vacancies or all the needs that are that are required to fulfill the work but that's why we have some flexibility to work with outside contractors and outside consultants as well if if suddenly we get oversight agencies that are quick in their review and get things done a bit faster that generally means we can accelerate or move a project forward faster but that also means we need to calculate do we have this staff internally to manage that work do we go outside to do that work or not rarely is that the case although there have been several cases in especially in in wastewater in the last couple of years where things have gotten accelerated but similarly there
are things that get delayed thank you so now I'd like to talk about our water
system our water system has two plants one on the Conestoga River and one on the Susquehanna River combined they can produce 36 million gallons of water a day we also have one reservoir oyster point five water tanks and four pump stations as well as hundreds of miles of pipe underground we serve over excuse me we serve over 120 000 people within the city and the surrounding municipalities our investment drivers in water are replacing our aging infrastructure we've been producing water since the late 1800s at the conestoga site now granted we don't have the same plant but that's how long we've been producing water our susquehanna plant was built in the 1950s so when you start thinking about it all of a sudden that's 80 years ago so we have what we'll talk about tonight is some of our larger projects which is to replace transmission lanes lines that are now 80 years old and you don't think about how you know how long we've been producing water in the city but water right now is facing many state and federal regulations most recently we had the improved lead and copper rule and they did call it that the improved lead and copper rule what the improvement was is that we had to replace all lead service lines within 10 years the first regulation that came out required it in 30 years so our timelines for work have significantly decreased we did an inventory initial inventory that we submitted last year we have a new inventory due in October of 2027 and then all those lines have to be replaced by 2037 and certainly you've seen us all over the website in media you know we're asking our water customers to please identify their service line in their homes so those efforts will continue the other significant regulatory redriver is the maximum contaminant levels we call these mcls for pfos and pfoa and those are the forever chemicals they were passed in january 14th of 2023 it's required quarterly monitoring at the entry points of our water into the system at both treatment plants we've been very successful in our monitoring efforts on the susquehanna river or excuse me the susquehanna plant which takes water from the susquehanna river we've been well under these mcls however as we saw the effects of the drought over the past year we saw the levels of pifoa increase at the con in the conestoga river for customers served by the conestoga plant these are significant regulatory drivers we've been told by the padep that they expect us you know to be in compliance we haven't negotiated any consent decrees or agreements at this point in time we've just been put on notice but we are planning for long-term compliance because on the federal level they have published even more stringent regulations at four parts per trillion and these will be effective in april of 2029 so we have two drivers here on the state level a requirement that's in effect now and one on the federal level in 2029 there's certainly been a lot in the news about the concern of forever chemicals our monitoring and planning continues to achieve compliance with these standards and it's put water companies throughout the nation at a disadvantage where we're treating for a contaminant that we never created it's not naturally occurring it was a man-made chemical and now we're all forced to address it accordingly with regulations another significant driver has been the drought and water withdrawal the city is regulated by this by the dep in pennsylvania on how much it can withdraw from the conestoga river and over the next 25 years they expect us to withdraw less so that as climate change occurs and there are droughts from time to time we will be constrained by how much water we can pull out of the river so we're looking at long-term planning to address that too so now i'd like to get into the projects next slide please our first two projects are to replace those 1950 error transmission lanes from the susquehanna plant we're looking at phase two the line that runs from the susquehanna treatment plant to the oyster point reservoir and phase three is the raw water transmission main from the intake on the susquehanna river to the treatment plant so these two projects um we've um we're in right now permitting with dep and we do expect to go out to bid late in the year early next year pending approval of our penvest loan we do expect to go seek penvest financing for these two particular projects our next project is the lead service line this particular project will not be spent all at once we'll have a series of small smaller projects as we submit for funding to the pen best authority we've recently been successful on a small project in the city of about a hundred and some hundred lines where we did get part grant funding and part loan funding so we'll be doing similar investments over the next couple years our next project is the south pump station which will start later in 2028 this station will help feed the new south tank the next are the lead service line improvements near term when this was ranked highest to lowest that's why the the two projects kind of separated the next project is the intake for the susquehanna low service pump station this screens the water as it comes into the pump station and then it's pumped to the plant we have placeholders for replacement of transite water pipe within the distribution system the next is water quality improvements at lafayette tank which also are driven by water quality regulations the next is a placeholder for cleaning and lining pipes in the distribution system the next is handling solids at the conestoga plant to improve our treatment system the next is at the conestoga plant rehabbing the tanks that are in the treatment system they're the rapid mix and equalization tanks next slide please this project is replacement of the large cast iron mains that are near the water plant these are big distribution mains this is a design of the pfas compliance our preliminary solution is that we will be looking at taking water from the susquehanna river instead of the conestoga river we'll be basically putting in another line a set of lines to bring water into the plant the next is the conestoga membrane replacement the cast iron pipe and materials are for city crews for for self-performance of work in within the city the conestoga clear well coating replacement is next the other two are to replace the next one is factors for transmission and distribution this is for our crews in the performance of their duties the susquehanna water treatment plant clear well relining very similar to the conestoga the clear wells are what hold the finished water they are anywhere from 80 years old 200 years old in age so we'll be doing a major project of um rehabilitating the concrete and then coating that concrete this will extend the life of the the tanks the next is replacing electrical equipment at the conestoga water treatment plant the next one is a placeholder for lead service line customer reimbursements we are required under the pennsylvania public utilities the puc to replace lead lines on either side of the of the service lateral not only what the city owns but what the customer owns and this is a placeholder for lead line replacements that customers had done since the promulgation of the regulations of the pc the next project is the oyster point reservoir clean out we'll be cleaning out the reservoir while it's still online using either divers or drones we'll be bidding that project out and then doing a structural inspection of the uh of the tank the reservoir tank in our last project um we basically summarized a lot of small water projects within the collect within the transmission and distribution system the plants to kind of roll it up so we wouldn't be into so water has significant investment it takes a lot to treat water thank you very much and it every time i see these numbers i'm reminded of
exactly how much we have invested into this this resource so thank you for that counselors anything on the last uh set of slides thank you very much this unless there's anything that you would like to add at the end it is a public hearing so we will hear any comments from the public but i just want to make sure you had an opportunity to finish your presentation if there was anything else
this does conclude the presentation i do ask the people if there's things that you want presented in a different way as we go forward we're in the process of building the foundation of how we talk about the capital planning process and how you want to receive data and information great so we
want to be careful about that thank you very much yes so this is a public hearing on the capital budget so comments around presentation of information would be appropriate at this point if there are any folks can join us at the microphone there you'll need to turn it back on and anyone who's sitting here will turn their mics off while that's so we don't get cross that's our theory are there any comments on the capital uh improvement plan hearing council president
while the public makes their way up sure if i may just wanted to express my gratitude to the public work scene for putting this presentation together and uh clearly for all the work that you guys do
on a day-to-day basis thank you thank you uh for those making public comment this evening i'll reiterate from earlier please begin with your name block of residence and uh three minute timer good
evening evening tony daschle 700 block of new holland avenue so it's greatly ironic that tonight we hear the capital budget hearing when as we just heard water is expensive and the public's looking at a massive data center which sure it may initially be air-cooled but these sort of systems unregulated may produce great burden to our water system and since water is expensive what can not only the rate payers of lancaster city but the rate payers of the entire area serviced by the city expect if there is a massive use that's going to use a considerable amount of water if we don't put in place now regulations to ensure that they if they're going to be water cooled use non-potable water regulations like that could maybe even be advantageous to meeting our consent decree we have hundreds of thousands of gallons we have to reduce and this private investment that's coming to our community which has very little regard for what we need as a public there's nothing in place to protect us this whole presentation is valued but it's terrifying in the face of these private investments that are going unregulated so I am curious if the Public Works Department has been made aware of these plans and if so when those are my comments and questions thank you Thank
You mr. Dastra any additional comment excuse me on the capital improvement
plan specifically good evening good evening Taylor Raymond 500 block of st. Joseph Street is this presentation going to be available on the website that's
all I really is it possible that this would be I'm assuming it will be on the
Public Works yes okay that was everything thanks thank you yes similar
to how the original list of projects was made available on June 30th I appreciate
that thank you any additional public comments on the capital improvement plan
good evening hi again Emma Burgess 600 West Vine Street my comment is I came here to yell about the AI Denison data center and I heard this presentation as well and I loved it so thank you for giving that I learned so much that's my
comment Thank You public officials thank you it's it's not all sexy but I mean I think the wastewater stuff is fascinating so that whatever that says about me but thank you for that any additional comments on the hearing I'm sorry yes so the the rest of our agenda will proceed including our legislative agenda which we have not yet gotten to tonight I'll remind everybody second public comment period report of the mayor council comments and adjournment so yes if there are no other comments for the capital improvement hearing we will close it and i will thank you all for your your hard work and dedication on this as i'm listening to this i'm reminded that other cities don't have this type of planning in place and it is we are fortunate to be able to think this far ahead so thank you i'll leave it at that
very much we really appreciate the opportunity to make it as transparent as practical to the
public what we do and how we do it thank you counselors the next item on our agenda is interim reports of committees of council of which we have none this evening so we will move then into our legislative agenda the first item is resolutions making sure that mr harris has the screen the screen back up and that he's ready of which we have one this evening the uh the one and only is administration resolution number 52 2025 when you're ready mr harris yes madam president
a resolution of the council in the city of lancaster authorizing the filing of an application for funding through the commonwealth financing authority multimodal transportation fund program in an amount not to exceed 2.8 million most to approve second we have a motion and a second and
i apologize i don't recall if this is coming up through public works or finance public works public
works council hirsch thank you thank you council president this resolution authorizes the city of lancaster to enter into a grant application to apply for the grant through the commonwealth financing authorities multimodal transportation fund this is in relation to the eastbound connector which is in the interim going to be a series of bike lanes and routes that get going eastward out of the city to to kind of stoga pines park and then ultimately the plan is to get to the go path from there out in east lampeter township the amount is for this grant not to exceed 2.8 million dollars if you recall in our committee that had not been established but it is entered into here and the only other comment i'll add correct me if i'm wrong director campbell but but I believe this is in almost as a follow-up to previous grant funding we had received and we were actually asked to or invited to apply again, which is exciting and the city is obviously coordinating with Maynard Township and Lancaster Township as well because they are also involved. And I think from what I've gathered in our conversations, Director Campbell, it's going to be a lot of, again, interim strategy towards a longer term project of how to make that connection work because it's it's definitely complicated between getting through the conestoga river and some of the other obstacles in that particular area so this is um hopefully going to go towards connecting
thank you very much counselor hirsch director campbell if you have anything additional
yes thank you i'm often amazed at how well you you are able to encapsulate the the core of what we're doing here this is in fact um the the implementation this would in fact be the implementation dollars to actually do the construction we have money that we've we've put together from previous grants and from the 2022 bond and 2025 bond to be able to to do the design work and work with the adjacent municipalities this is part of trying to complete or or finish off some of the connections between the city's active transportation network infrastructure and the county active transportation network as well this is what's going to make lancaster that much more magical as a place to live work and play so i just wanted to give a little bit of that as an enhancement to the to what you would describe thank you thank you very
much director Campbell councillors are there any additional comments on the resolution comments on the resolution from the public hearing none mr. Harris
mr. man hi mr. Roya aye mr. Gleason aye miss Craig all right miss Diaz aye mr. Hirsch aye aye thank you that concludes our legislative
agenda for this evening we'll take us to our second public comment period this is open for comment on issues not previously on the agenda duration of comments is limited to three minutes per speaker for those wishing to make public comment during this period please proceed to the microphone at this time begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting record good
evening good evening my name is Julie Zug I'm living at the zero block of East Walnut Street and I came here planning only to listen and learn with some concerns about the data center these are just a few of the puzzle pieces i've picked up this evening now the proposed location of the data center the lsc communications property on greenfield road was recently reported as being the other lsc communications property on harrisburg pipe which is lancaster city but greenfield if i'm not mistaken is lancaster township no it's not it's in the city okay i was looking at it it's on the line between slam peter and the city okay all right um however this property is located according to the maps i've looked at um on greenfield road however it's across the street from the conestoga pines pool which the city appears to be ready to study into relocating but still it's included in consideration of the capital budget um for their uh for the eastbound connector plan and i'm not sure i understand how that's working if that's part of something that you're planning on relocating now the developer of this data center machine investment group a simple google search a new york based in real estate investment platform which according to their own website is focused on opportunistic distressed and special situations across the united states they were formed by former senior executives of garrison investment group a delaware llc also out of new york which was sanctioned in september of 2022 for failing to have required audits performed and to deliver the audited financials to investors i would i would urge our city and anyone involved in planning this thing to stop selling our city out to the to the investment bankers thank you
thank you good evening here are the 200 block of north concord street and this is about the data center also there was a long article thank you i have a no i have a scratchy voice anyway A long article in the May 25th in Time magazine about the data center in Granbury, Texas. And here ours is also going to be air cooled. Will there be fans and noise, excessive and unhealthy noise, running 24 hours a day, seven days a week? Where is all this electricity coming from? Do we have the local infrastructure for it? And who is going to be paying for all the usage? All of us need electricity to run our houses. What equivalent household usage in water and power will the data center be using? The issue is when the data center consumes water and electricity, how will that affect our domestic supply and our costs? staying in the building's old footprint at the old printing plant so that they do not need approval i don't really understand the approval process seems that we do not have sufficient information if we don't know what's going on what's happening how are we lancaster city going to deal with it if you have nothing to say about what's going on in granbury texas which is not too far from fort worth which is a big city there have been very strange medical emergencies from the thousands of fans emitting a constant buzz i am sure our citizens don't want to be living in some strange unhealthy episode of the twilight zone thank you good evening good evening my name is daryl legacy
i'm from the 100 block of north mary and i didn't initially come to see all of the capital plan but i'm glad i did because a lot of it was actually really interesting and helpful and there also are parts of that that i think apply to the data center one of which is spending four hundred thousand dollars on conestoga pines which is right next door and i question how much that park is going to be used when there are fans going 24 7 right next to it and i think that's something we should be considering when we're determining whether we're going to spend that money i also think what's really interesting to me is that we have to do a land development plan for buying that one little strip from ppl but the data center doesn't that means we as the city are doing a development plan for ourselves as the city that this external company does not need to do i think that is a huge problem and that's indicative of what is happening here that is problematic i think there everybody that has spoken has done a good job already explaining most of the issues there are a couple things that haven't come up if you go to the charissa website which they're the company that's developing this they say Lancaster East which I assume is the Greenfield but they also say Lancaster West so even though there's nothing official on their website it says Lancaster West under development you can all go see that right now so they are planning what I assume is the 1375 Harrisburg Pike location regardless of whether they've said they are doing that or not they're telling you on their website they're doing it and that is right next to longs park like does everybody realize is right next to longs park so i have some questions that i think need to be considered in addition to the ones that people have already said one is who is going to be responsible to see if they expand past the existing footprint thereby triggering the land development plan the wastewater treatment plan and all of these things they are going to have to do i mean who is going to be measuring did they they expand past the existing footprint and it has to be us it has to be the city I don't trust them I think and I'm sure they're gonna say no no we didn't and I don't think we should be trusting them enough also I think we need to think about the one especially at Harrisburg Pike but probably the one near in Greenfield as well have they done any studies on animal impact there are many many many migratory birds that are in Longs Park are they affected will they be affected by this semi-secret location that they're clearly planning to do? And I think that's something that we need to be thinking about. I also think we should be thinking about the impact of construction. What's going to happen, not only Greenfield, but Harrisburg Pike? I mean, what's going to happen when you're literally talking next door to Longs Park? Huge construction equipment, I would assume for years, potentially building this location. And I just think those are extra questions you should all be asking and we should all be thinking about. And I don't think should be moving ahead until we have answers thank you good evening am i good um brittany
mitchell uh 400 block of east grant street um and i also wasn't planning on speaking today so i'm just gonna kind of go for it and say what's in my heart um i just hearing the report from president vacay uh with a lot of those really sort of nice comforting uh details about you know the cooling span and and and all the reasons why the water is going to be okay and all that stuff i just can't help but wonder what about our any experience uh that we've had in in our country with unmitigated capitalistic self-interest in an environment that is completely devoid of any regulations would make us think that we should trust or listen to that something about me is I probably have plastics in my brain most of you guys probably do too you know micro plastics are in all of us and I'm sure decades ago those companies would have said hey everything's hunky-dory check out our cool fan we'll write you a nice little check and whatever else they would have had to say to get their foot in the door and now it's too late i don't know what that's going to do to us long term we don't have a lot of you know scientific data on uh on microplastics but we're still kind of in that find out era and it's not looking good i don't have any children but i care about your kids and i'm not willing to sign them up to be a real-time experiment of how much poison air you can breathe um i hope that you guys aren't willing to do that either because this is the thing that once we let it into our community we're not going to be able to undo it those effects are going to be real so i'm not naive i hope that you guys aren't either I just hope that you can, you know, be honest with yourselves about what you are about to let into the community where we all have to live every day. Thank you.
Thank you.
Tony D'Astra, 700 block of New Holland Avenue. I'm glad Watergate got brought up earlier because there's a favorite song of mine by Stevie Wonder that was written for Richard Nixon. It's called You Haven't Done Nothing.
first eight lines go like this we are amazed but not amused by all the things
you'll say that you'll do though much concern but not involved with decisions that are made by you but we are sick and tired of hearing your song telling how you are gonna change right from wrong cuz if you really want to hear our views you haven't done nothing and that's the case here we have an opportunity to let this go through a use not provided for process as our zoning ordinance dictates instead we've said screw all the red tape and I think that's insane because the use that this is provided for so it has additional words behind it they were not an LMP one of those being an exclusion for processing data is being processed i don't care that it's not something we can physically hold those storage blocks and the heat they produce are very real this issue is very real this issue is very concerning and if you care about working families at all you need to do something now you need to speak out now because people are about to be greatly hurt financially their health the fact that people have to come to this board this board meeting this council meeting just to feel like they have the possibility of being hurt this is the same city council i'm frustrated with for trying to gut the tree ordinance environmental issues have always been a secondary priority in the last i don't know handful of years we have a comprehensive plan that talks about eco districts and i'm still mad at the planning commission which i'm a part of for not amending the zoning ordinances to this day everyone here should be mad at the planning commission too we have a significant amount of work to do but we were too concerned about giving people city council districts things like that this is a shame and the fact that you're trying to distance yourselves from this is an abhorrent use of words good evening hello my name is christina sudorescu
I actually live close to Centerville, but I, you know, work and live in Lancaster City. So I was an undergraduate and a master's graduate of Carnegie Mellon University where CoreWeave recently announced their intention to use Lancaster County in their AI expansion plan. For years as a student there, we weren't just educated on the beneficial uses of AI. We were also taught the full picture of all that comes with AI, including the negative implications that are impossible to separate from the good stuff. I appreciate your notes earlier today about, you know, the press release that happened very recently. Some part of me, like, believes you when you say a lot of you just recently heard about this in terms of the transparency. but it is odd to hear you know the words transparency and the surprise update of construction having started already in the same sentence so I kind of wonder what your response your accountability procedures are in order to make sure that you know those other parties do uphold transparency so with all of this updates it feels remarkably fast for something that will forever change the landscape of our city. So I want to address my statement to Lancaster itself, the city that raised me, and the place that gave me real tangible things to value. I moved back home from after living in a big city after four years of college, and I uprooted my community and life there, you know, to come back home. And sometimes you don't really appreciate what you have until you move away and you can't find it anywhere else on my move back i drove through 44 contiguous states like hoping that a city would surprise me and um you know call me to its home but nowhere is like lancaster some of my friends in new york or philadelphia come to lancaster specifically for the amazing dairy for the fresh fruits and vegetables that come at an unbeatable price some of my friends in los angeles asked me to flip the camera when i facetimed them because they can't believe they can't fathom how close I live to agriculture and nature day by day the fields the pastures the silos the bucolic scenery the backyards the nature trails the central market the Amish people this is my love letter to you Lancaster and it is my love that I ask everyone to consider do we really need to force ourselves to be on the map as it relates to higher tech jobs why should we sacrifice what makes us honest what makes what increases the quality of our lives in order to perpetuate a faster and frankly crappier lifestyle um what good is you know a single you know few billion dollar investment when it sacrifices the multi billion we make annually on agriculture food processing tourism and other related sectors i'm really happy memphis came up earlier um because that colossus computer uh has access to 50 megawatts of energy um and they you know were petitioning to try to get up to 150. i appreciate your comments but we've reached three minutes okay ours is 100 and it goes to 300 so
thank you good evening good evening taylor raymond 500 block of saint joseph street um i'd like to first start by saying that i agree with several community members who have come up and requested a change in our zoning laws to exclude the data center as the wholesale trade and storage. Some place like this needs significantly more oversight than it has. The data centers will, sorry, they contribute to a rise in greenhouse gases like CO2. As the growth of AI continues to rise, we cannot keep up with sustainable energy to cover the difference, so it's going to increase the effects of climate change locally and globally, which is going to have an outsized impact on our poorest residents, including the ones who live outside, they are not very well-regulated by any government, but there are some governments that we can look to for groundwork, essentially, notably Ireland, the EU AI Act, and Senator Ed Markey, who's a Democrat, he's pushing for more info and sustainability on AI I think that we should be following suit and we shouldn't allow this data center I as I said at the last City Council meeting I work at the Lancaster County Tax Collection Bureau which is less than a mile as the crow flies from the Greenfield Road data center area so not only do I live in the city I work so clear so close and as you said it's it straddles the line of East Lampeter earth yes East Lampeter so it affects not only city residents but anybody who works in the city anybody who lives or works in East Lampeter I don't think that we should allow this because it affects so much more than we have any control at City Council over yeah that is everything I've got thank you good evening
Ellen Sloan I live in the first block of North Lyme Street I'm not going to talk about the data center I'm going to talk about something I talked about two weeks ago and I'll keep talking about it until I get some kind of response I'm here once again to speak about ice as you may be aware the budget reconciliation bill signed into law this month allocates a 45 billion dollars for building new immigration detention centers which represents a 265 percent annual budget increase it is a 62 percent larger budget than the entire federal prison system b almost 30 billion dollars towards ice enforcement and deportation operations a three-fold increase in ice's annual budget all this while also capping the number of immigration judges at 800, despite the record backlogs. The Trump administration means business. Lancaster calls itself a welcoming city. Some call Lancaster the refugee capital of the United States. Who among us here tonight would deny that immigrants have enriched our community beyond measure? We must do what we can to protect the folks who have come here from places of pain and struggle looking simply for a place to live in peace i am once again asking the city council to pass an ordinance a requiring visible identification for all law enforcement agents operating within the city including federal agents and prohibiting facial concealment of said officers b banning our local police from cooperating with ice agents especially without warrants or legal clear legal justification and c also to work with city schools and hospitals to develop protective policies and rapid response systems when federal ice agents show up i'm sure you have seen the horrific videos of people being snatched off the streets or at courthouses or their places of work by masked individuals with frightening weapons disappeared no due process sent to prisons far away perhaps never to see their loved ones again we have seen the unwanted militarization of los angeles is this what we want in our city secret police disappearing people please act before it is too late they are coming for immigrants now who will they come for next thank you thank you are there any additional comments for this period
Good evening.
My name is Robert McLean, 123 South Christian. And I'm here, basically, I have a little sign I've been showing around. It's called democracynow.org. You can get that on your computer. What you're talking about, as far as this AI in this area, is the tip of the iceberg. You don't have any idea, and nobody else has any idea, how it's going to turn out. This woman, Karen Ho, wrote a book to explain it, and she's from China, Hong Kong. She's back and forth in the United States. She has scared the devil out of the people who have heard her speech. And you can get a synopsis of the book on democracynow.org. Just hit AI. And you will get the whole book in one hour's time. But everyone should have this. Find your way through examining what she's saying. She's a Chinese person who wrote this over 20 years of work. She knows what she's talking about. And we are all going to suffer in the long run and never get out of it. Because it's not going to financially destroy us. There's valleys up in northern PA, a whole valley for transmission lines, big ones, to carry AI line energy. The whole valley was threatened to be condemned for this AI business. That's what's happening around the world. This is an international station around the world. It's happening around the world, not just in this area.
we will actually the easiest way to get that to us is through mr harris and he will give us that send us that information thank you so much are there any additional comments for this period hearing none we will close the second public comment period thank you again the next item on our agenda is the report of the mayor mayor sirachi i don't have a report this evening given uh the late hour thank you very much the next item was the report of the president of council which i delivered at the beginning of the meeting and the last item then before adjournment is council comments counselors any comments this evening outside of our agenda
counselor ahmed thank you council president and as this is an ongoing issue where we are learning more each day i would hope that council can receive a report on what options council does have what are the current situation regarding the data centers to help make sure that council knows what we can do to protect the city's interest moving forward and also alleviate some of the concerns that community members have shared so um thank you that concludes my comments
thank you counselor med any additional council comments hearing none having reached the conclusion of our agenda counselors i'll hear a motion to adjourn motion to adjourn i have a motion and a second all in favor aye we are adjourned thank you